[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right so we have about 30 people
rsvp'd
so usually half show so i imagine this
will
be it and more people might trickle in
which is good because this
is going to be a somewhat of a different
session um
from our regular stoa sessions uh so
first welcome to the stoa i'm pete
lindbergh the steward of the store
and uh today we have uh my good
buddy tim adeline from voice craft
collective
in the house or in the store i should
say um
so this is a true story so there's like
out of all the psycho technologies that
we have
at the stoa um my favorite one is just
really it doesn't belong in one of our
wisdom gyms just smoking a cigar
and having whiskey i love that that
that's my favorite psycho technology
my second favorite psycho technology is
listening to tim speak
it's just kind of riding that wave of uh
where he takes you
um so how today is going to work is
tim is going to share his thoughts on
uh the topic at hand and the topic is
painting with words loving
transformation or something
um and that or something part i don't
know if that was your intention to put
that in or i just misread your email
okay
i'm bad um and uh and then
that he'll he'll talk around the 20 30
minute mark and then the remainder time
we are going to have a collective
dialogue so we'll have a moment of
silence
and i'll repeat this afterwards we have
a moment of silence um
and whoever feels called to make a
statement
ask a question whatever it may be a
question to tim
question to the group uh just unmute
yourself and
uh make your statement ask your question
we should do this a lot before uh
tim was at a lot of these sessions uh
before stoa
and my old group um they're quite fun
and they're quite alive and it's
leans on some of the collective
presenting kind of tech that we do as
well
so that's the second half of this uh i
was thinking
like we're definitely gonna record the
first half we might not record the
second half uh but i'll just leave the
record on
but if you feel strongly uh about not
being uh on the recording just
message me privately and then i'll just
pause the recording at that mark
so that being said oh
tim i'll take you in my friend welcome
to oh i was trying to get tim on the
stove since this all started so i'm so
happy you're here
yeah thank you peter it's lovely to be
here can't believe how
how quickly the year's gone how much
things have grown here
and uh yeah man it's uh it's a privilege
and an honor to be honest
um i thought i'd begin just obviously
saying hello to everyone
and um just to appreciate the
the attention fundamentally i think
the um the background idea to
what i want to discuss and explore
with you all today is really
just how much the context matters now we
hear that a lot
but i mean it in the sense that um in
preparing for this
there's a sense in which i couldn't
actually prepare what it is i truly have
to say
outside of being here with you all
there's a sense of um
meeting the moment and finding out
essentially who i am
here that is deeply
relevant i has something i think to do
with the imminence of life
and really being on the pulse
of who you are in relationship
so fundamentally what i want to talk
about is some of the most
important things to me so it's like
how do you begin something like that
because
these aren't things i can box up easily
you know these are the kinds of things
that
i i've come to rely on in the
most difficult moments of my life and
the kinds of things that
you know i could say to you with honesty
if i was to peel back
myself what would there be you know
speak about
notions like soul like what is that
you know not something you can box up
not something you can point at
you know we're doubtful it exists and
what's your epistemology what's your
ontology you know
these words they are such traps at times
and we can forget what really matters
and we can forget what
um we really are when we are simply
here and present and witnessing the
unfolding
of soul in relationship
so it's in that sense that um
only really together here can this be
what it is
and i expect actually in many ways
what i have to say might not land uh
perhaps even most of the time
um but the hope is that um
if we can participate in the process
together if we can
deeply listen then maybe there'll be
something
from me to you and between us that can
connect perhaps some of the deepest
thoughts that there are
so
you know i used to go for um walks with
a good friend of mine his name's nick
when i was studying in england for my
master's it means to
take different dosages of mushrooms and
go for
walks um late at night through forests
and over bridges in bristol and
remember walking through storms and
there was
a mode of expression that came to me
because we'd have
similar conversations you know and uh
we'd begin them and i would begin being
so confused at times like you make it to
a point of deep understanding
right you're in some sort of coherence
with one another things seem to fit
together
and then part of you is wondering well
why can't i why can't i be right there
again right now right i'm all of a
sudden confused again
and whereas i felt so connected before
somehow the world
fit together so we've forgotten
and then the remembering process it's
not something you want to put the cart
before the horse with
right there's a certain sense in which
that dark garden
um can be illuminated but you have to
walk through it sort of with humility
and authentically again um
you might know some things about it but
you have to be in touch with it
and so it's something like that it's
something like um
stepping into a dark garden
one that i've been in many times before
that i am i suppose i'm proposing to do
with you today
and the uh the the notion in the title
um loving transformation is something
that i've
written about so much you know but in in
the most
private way and uh i can't do it justice
here with you
i suppose because it's something well
actually i can you know i can do my best
but i don't expect to come to
completeness with it
you know if someone was to ask me what's
fundamentally going on
and was to really push me on that as
though i had to squeeze out
what there is into a proposition i would
probably rest on
loving transformation um but of course
that's just a word
you know they're just words and uh
perhaps we can make sense of them
together
so
hmm
it seems fundamentally we go through
movements as i said before of of uh
remembering and forgetting of um
holding and letting go stepping forward
and
being in a right relationship where the
kind of ember of truth of what we have
to express
like our moment of expression with
someone
or activity just as it is is appropriate
and then all of a sudden it's like oh
maybe i need to be quiet now in fact
maybe that was inaccurate maybe that was
somehow not true
and i have to listen i have to take in
more information and i have to
essentially let go
of this mode of orientation
i had to the world previously and so we
attach and we detach
you know and this language is common
you hear it all all around the place in
buddhism and what have you
so something like love captures this for
me
because we might ask what is it to love
and you might have heard forest laundry
is now
i suppose semi-famous phrase in circles
like this which is
love is that which enables choice which
i think is a beautiful expression
you know it might not necessarily
capture the
the the poetic effectiveness of what it
is to
really be an imminent imminent touch
with someone
um or the world you know but i think it
offers a helpful way in
because when we think about
[Music]
loving and letting go sort of
deeply affirming the nature of something
enabling its choice enabling it to be
what it is well we we realized that
in some instances that is very much a
holding and in others
we have to let go and
be what it is and all of a sudden our
paths are no longer together
and that's very hard to accept you know
it's very very hard to accept letting go
of things
whether it's power or identity um
almost anything at all of worth
and perhaps there you know the
forgetting is so important it's i resist
going to sleep
a lot myself but there's a certain sense
in which you go
to sleep you get to drop a lot of the
baggage a bunch of the processing is
done unconsciously and we get to go
again
we have this built-in change of
consciousness it's it's as though
um being
absolutely on the pulse of things
in their center if you like is um
is not sustainable and it's not really
perhaps even possible
so we are things then that are moving
you know um i think a lot about the
notion of integrity
something you also hear as a core value
that someone like greg enriquez will
speak about or
jordan hall these sorts of circles
i relate to integrity as the
capacity to sense where the moving
center is
not in a way that can be understood to
be static
but in a way that's dynamic and
it's that orientation back to
what is then the wandering center that
is an orientation towards wholeness
as a whole making
and what do these words sort of mean
i think i mean in the broadest possible
sense
you know we've had these philosophical
theories of
various kinds of monism and dualism and
sometimes kind of funny to think about
because it's like is it all one thing or
is it like two things man like
we're all just stuck on that um
and most people these days are like oh
it's definitely one thing it's just like
many ways that one thing can be
and i'm in that camp you know but what
does that explain
well in some sense it means that in some
nebulous sense
we're all connected but then people
argue about
just what that connectedness means and
we have some sort of understanding that
well you've got to be
at some kind of level of development to
understand this pattern of how we're all
connected and whatever
but then we can think about stardust and
the way
different energy flows
through different substances affect us
and
and through which we participate
in ecology and all of the dynamic
processes which give rise to us
and so in this sense
a moving processual whole
these interrelated processes that
are as they are and give rise to us
through that
what is it to be in dedication to those
i would say is something like
something like what is it to be
life affirming in the broadest possible
sense
and that when we forget somehow
of our connectedness connectedness to
what is
um whole whole making
in our proximal environment and then
more broadly
this is akin to a cutting you know a
forgetting as a kind of cutting
and um paradoxically also a sort of
holding on to because we
we perhaps we forget that really to
to remember is to let go as well
you know and is to to accept a
process of living and dying and change
and so i
i think about these things and um
and i find them manifest most helpfully
not as words but as but as
um movement in
the very heart of um
you might say chaos or void and
um that's an awful lot of movement
anyway you might think just not of any
ordered kind it can be in coherent
relationship to
how does the sort of but i think that
the matter is how the psyche kind of
hangs together
and how um we can in some sense
hold hands with each other in
relationship to all that swirling around
us
so i don't mean to communicate by this
that in some sense um
who we are in relation to the world is
in is uh
should be conceived only as relative
i actually think in this kind of
perspective we can
um we can relate to something
more true and more grounded than that
and it is
in the dynamics of what enables
relationship
itself to endure but not from a sense of
what is me and mine in a fixed sense
cut but what is
well the we to participate in
and
that seems to be one of the fundamental
challenges of course something i see
many of the conversations and sessions
here at the store
um orient around in some sense how can
we
come into relationship with something
greater than ourselves
of course unless we do this we're all
fundamentally
but by fact in this case i mean you know
things might not go
well by ordinary measures of success
but perhaps in fact it's um
there's plenty of room for deep hope
because
there's something to
there's something to the process of
moving
energy appropriately within and with
each other
that it's like it um
it's like we have this transcendental
capacity
to to
accept our conditions and transcend them
and that doing that is fundamentally
meaningful
you know we can care for each other in
the face of
the worst of things
and so an attendance to what
is is the relationship
the the vitality in it is
is the direction fundamentally i
to orient and um
so something like this is is the
beginnings of
how i relate to this notion like loving
transformation it's
it's the perpetual pattern of um
affirming and letting go it is um
what is and what has been and what must
be
in order for there to be anything at all
anything coherent at all
but these are just words you know
there's something to
[Music]
like like an intuition in in the mind's
eye
like a um like the wisp of a dream
that i relate to
at times when i've essentially all but
forgotten
just why the hell to continue on at all
really in the face of so much craziness
and it's being um
honest to that sense that i trust
which you know leads to um
which leads back in some sense to what i
began speaking about which is the sort
of
the context of this little container
here with just the 20 of us
in this room just for this moment and
then it passes away
[Music]
because
it's again it's it's what we
it's what we realize here together that
fundamentally matters and it's through
that
orientation that necessarily everything
else comes
so i put here a few
slightly grandiose things in this
description
an experimental piece of philosophy that
will seek to share images
movements and conceptions of response to
existential questions
of life and time questions of love death
and transformation
questions of teleology process and event
questions of meaning nihilism sacredness
and the absurd
i think maybe the notion of teleology is
something i'd like to say a few things
about
i don't know if i'll be able to i don't
know if i'll be able to um
fit with the various ideas that have
locked into me
over the years to this moment here
but this notion of teleology is
something
um most are deeply skeptical of
you know at the moment it's something
that um john viveki for instance
uh such a wonderful teacher he's very
skeptical of
you know that there's teleology meaning
some kind of
um end state or or purpose
conceived as the arrival and end state
um you know
there's a sense there that um well
that's maybe sounding too objective like
it was all made by
some sort of creator or um
that there's an essential essence to
what it is to
um to purpose um
or fittedness even and that's not what
um some think about that
but the way i relate to this is in some
sense that it's
deeply central to what it is to be in
meaningful relationship with the world
but that it's it's not about some
final end point that was set before us
precisely but is something to be
ongoingly realized as we develop
in relationship with the world and each
other
and said like that
it's something that um john might well
agree with
but i but i i don't think that the
that the setting of these goals
that the envisioning of these end states
is
um in some sense just hanging
or or um entirely contingent
um it seems that there are
uh appropriate orientations
in relationship given specific contexts
that develop as a result of we might say
shifts in
culture or technology or nature levels
of complexity
fields of possibility open up which have
certain kinds of niches
and only through a certain sort of
ethics of interaction in this new field
can life in the only way we can relate
to it
continue i don't mean to say this in
some sort of anthropocentric sense
but it does deeply seem to be that the
ethics of interaction
are fundamentally bound up with
how it is we can realize what to aim at
together
even in the understanding that that is
to be reimagined as we go
but it's it's nevertheless a a real
thing a real relationship
with potential um
and so i think we
i think there's something to this notion
of teleology that's not to entirely be
put away just yet
and um and it's something like that too
that i work into this notion of
loving transformation um
the the inherent dynamic
that um enables
life the inherent it you can think of it
as almost like a
a will of a kind of a vital pulse
you know a will to life but but one that
is not um uh
one kind of thing but has many natures
that interrelate
and find themselves in relationship in
different
modes of orientation
so it looks to me you know
as we and and i should say as well that
that everything i've said so far i'm
inviting a kind of um participatory
listening to this i'm not um
really even suggesting that any term
i've used or even
necessarily any conception be the one or
is the one that we go i'll
point to that feeling or
that thing with with those words and
that concept you know i'm inviting that
to the extent that anything i've said
has triggered something that
connects something for you or moves you
to express in a way that's meaningful
that you
do so you know in in your own words
and that we enter into interaction with
each other
and come to understand what we really
mean
um
these the words essentially are an
invitation this is not
some kind of um uh it's
the opposite thing from a definitive
philosophical
talk you know where we're going to tie
this word to this concept and that's how
we're all going to relate
um so in that sense
uh watching my
girlfriend go through different
processes of
painting you know i've taken inspiration
from that and just
how i've tried to speak to you guys
today there are these layers of paint we
put down
and each
each stroke you know each each layer is
something that we
we put energy into and we feel into
and we express all that we can in the
imminence
of that moment and um
and we can see what emerges so that's
what i'm
inviting fundamentally that whatever
paint has been haphazardly
thrown at the wall here you know
i'm inviting you all to to share in that
and um perhaps see where we go
so thank you you know for being here
and your attention this would have been
fundamentally different
if uh if if you weren't here and um
that's a beautiful thing in some sense
so cheers peter
thank you tim so we're going to move to
the
second portion of the evening
and i think i'm going to return i turned
the record off um
because it makes it more i feel free us
up a little bit
um so what we're going to do we're going
to have a moment of silence
everyone's i'm going to be on on mute
and whoever feels sort of
called to say something uh
something that felt a lie for them when
they were listening to him talk
unmute yourself and say it could be a
question to tim to a group
uh or just a statement um and then i
meet yourself
and it's like popcorn style the next
person who wants to say something says
something
um so i'll stop uh recording right now
let's have a moment of silence and i
invite everyone to
turn on their camera and we're here for
another 30 minutes at least